Data science to me is more of, it's a tool in the toolbox, okay?
And so, as a carpenter,
you can build framing for houses,
you can build wooden fences,
you can make wonderful custom cabinetry,
you can make children's toys.
But all of that comes out of sort of having
that basic knowledge of how to use those woodworking tools.
But there's obviously a lot of mastery that goes into those different disciplines.
And so for us, it's more than just the knowledge of how to use these tools and
how to explore datasets and make meaningful predictions or pull insights from them,
but rather that has to be connected to medicine and biology,
and sort of this interpretive aspect of what we're doing.
And so when we look for people that we bring into our company from a science perspective,
not only do they have to have that meaningful understanding of
computer science and sort of how to use these toolsets,
but also, what are even the questions we want to ask of that data?
How are we going to construct these systems to sort of go
after solving these very complex biological problems?
We're looking for that capability in the mind of a single person.