We will now look at the empirical rule, and norm approximation for data.
This is an important technique in statistics, because it is used in many statistical procedures.
We will also discuss the binomial distribution, and some basic ideas about random variables.
It turns out that many data have histograms which have a very characteristic shape.
Heights, weights, IQ scores, and many other data have a histogram which has a bell shape.
The histogram that you see here shows the heights of 928 fathers that were collected
by Sir Francis Galton in the 19th century.
This is a typical example of a bell-shaped histogram.
In such a case, one says that the data follow the normal curve.
But keep in mind that some data have histograms that are quite different.
We already saw that when we looked at incomes.