Remember when we talked about graphical
summaries, we talked about the boxplot.
The boxplot shows five
numbers about the data.
The smallest number,
which is given on the lower whisker,
the 1st quartile up here, the median,
the 3rd quartile, and the largest number.
The distance between the 3rd quartile and
the 1st quartile tells you how
much the data is spread out.
This has a special name,
it's called the interquartile range.
When it comes to measuring
spread in the data,
it's more common to use a different
measure, namely the standard deviation.
You've probably seen the notation x bar,
which stands for
the average of a list of numbers.
Let's call them x1 to xn.
Here's the formula for
the standard deviation of these numbers.
It's not that important to remember
the formula, since calculators and
computers can compute it for you.
But let's just have a look what
the interpretation of that formula is.
What the standard deviation does
is it looks at the difference
of each number from its average,
squares the difference,
and then looks at the average
of those squared differences.
And finally, it takes the square root.
Sometimes, you see a formula that has
n-1 instead of n in the denominator.
Both of these formulas
work roughly equally well.
The mean and the standard deviation
are often used to summarize data.
The first one gives you
a measure of center, and
the second one gives a measure of spread.
Both can be sensitive to a few large or
small data,
just as we saw in the example before.
So if you're worried about that, for
example, if the histogram is very skewed,
then it may be better to use
the median and the interquartile range.
Of course, one problem is that many
people don't know what the median and
the interquartile range is.
So you may have to explain that.