You may have read in the news that people who eat red meat
have higher rates of certain cancers than people who don't eat red meat.
The statistical term for this is that
there's an association between red meat consumption and
cancer but it's important to keep in mind
that this does not mean that eating red meat causes cancer.
This is because people who don't eat red meat are known to exercise more and drink
less alcohol, and it could be
the latter two issues that caused the difference in cancer rates.
What we have here is called an observational study.
It simply measures the outcomes of interest.
In this case, it would measure the cancer rate among
people who eat red meat and the cancer rate among people who do not eat red meat.
Based on these measurements,
one can say whether there's an association between these two factors.
But as we saw before,
association does not mean causation because there may be other factors.
These are called confounding factors.
Sometimes they have the name lurking variable.
Now, what we really would like to know is whether eating red meat actually causes cancer.
For that, we need an experiment.
In an experiment, a treatment is actually
assigned to people in one group but not in the other group.
Treatment is a technical term.
For example, if we have a new medication against high blood pressure,
then the treatment would be to take this medication.
The group that gets the treatment is called
a treatment group, and the other group is called the control group.
After we assign the treatment,
we compare the outcomes in the two groups.
We have already seen that confounders can be a problem.
For that reason, the two groups should be similar.
Of course, the treatment is different in the two groups.
The best way to make sure that the two groups are similar is
to assign the persons into the two groups at random.
The way to think about the random assignment
is that for each subject we toss a coin and if
it comes up heads then the subject goes into
the treatment group and if it comes up tails it will go in the control group.
Another precaution we should take is
that every subject in the control group gets a placebo.
A placebo is very similar to the treatment but it doesn't do anything.
In the example where we want to test a new medication against high blood pressure,
the treatment might consist of a pill then the placebo
would also be a pill which doesn't have any medication in it.
Why would we do that?
It turns out that the idea of being treated may already have an effect by itself.
This is called the placebo effect.
Assigning a placebo to the control group makes sure
that both groups are equally affected by this placebo effect.
The third precaution is that the experiment should be double-blind.
That means that neither the subject nor the evaluators know
which subjects are assigned to the treatment, and which are assigned to control.
This is done to avoid biases.
For example, if a doctor has to evaluate whether their medication helped,
then the doctor might be inclined to give
a positive assessment if the doctor knows that the patient has received the treatment.
Let's briefly go back to the placebo effect.
It sounds a bit mysterious.
Indeed, the placebo effect is still not fully understood.
It's somewhere on the boundary between biology and
psychology, and it's probably one of the most interesting phenomena in science.
If you're interested more in reading about the placebo effect,
there's the accessible article, 'The weird power of
the placebo effect, explained' by Brian Resnick.