We have reached the end of the course.
We have discussed the key ideas for learning from data and assessing uncertainty.
We looked at the important concepts that are behind
almost every statistical inference, such as
the square root law and the basic rules of probability.
We also saw how modern computer-intensive procedures such as the bootstrap
can be a big help for inference.
We discussed the main statistical procedures that come
up in analyzing data such as regression,
testing, and the analysis of categorical data.
We also discussed how to effectively communicate information by visualizing data.
Even advanced methods in machine learning use
these basic ideas in one way or another, and chances are,
that when you look under the hood of new methodology that you encounter in the future,
you will recognize a number of ideas that we discussed in this course.
You now have the background to take the machine
learning course, or an advanced statistics course.
I wish you the best with your future learning.