Let's look again at the previous
example of tossing a coin 100 times.
If we are interested in
the number of tails,
there are the following possible outcomes.
We could get 0 tails or
1, or 2, up to 100.
Now how likely is each of these outcomes?
We know that this is the binomial
distribution with n = 100, and
p = 0.5.
Because if we call a coin landing
tails a success, then the number
of tails is simply the number
of successes in 100 experiments.
So if we are interested in the statistic
that counts the number of tails,
then this statistic is a random variable
whose probability histogram is
given by the binomial distribution.
This is called the sampling
distribution of the statistic.
The reason why we use a sampling
distribution is because it provides more
detailed information about the chance
properties of the statistic than
the summary numbers given by the expected
value and the standard error alone.