The technical term, distribution,
comes up in many different ways.
It's helpful to step back and see what's happening here.
When we toss the coin 100 times,
we simulate the data by drawing from the probability histogram.
That probability histogram says we can get
heads with probability a half and tails with probability a half.
So remember that the probability histogram is a theoretical construct.
It simply tells us what the chances are for simulating.
After we have simulated 100 tosses,
we have actual data.
For example, we could end up with 47 heads and 53 tails.
Then we can make a histogram of those data, and the histogram looks like this one.
So you see that this histogram looks quite
similar to the probability histogram in the first step,
but it's a little bit different because the 100 tosses involve a chance process.
Finally, if we are interested in a statistic,
such as the number of tails in 100 tosses,
then we get a third histogram,
which gives the sampling distribution of that statistic.
In this case, it's a binomial distribution,
and you'll see that this histogram is quite different from the first two.
Later on when we do statistical inference,
it's easy to mix up these histograms.
So it's really important to carefully think through what's going on there.