Computer power has revolutionized
statistical inference.
In this module, we look at the two main
concepts that are behind this revolution,
the Monte Carlo method and the bootstrap.
We will discuss the main principles
behind these methods and
then see how to apply them in
various important contexts,
such as in regression and for
constructing confidence intervals.
Remember that very simple formula for the
confidence interval for a population mean.
We simply take the sample mean
plus minus z times standard error.
The reason why we used z
was because the sample mean
approximately follows the normal curve.
Now what happens if we're interested
in a different estimator,
let's call it theta hat, for
some parameter, theta, of the population.
And the normal approximation is
not valid for this estimator.
In that case, such a simple formula
is not applicable anymore, and
we have to do something else.
Likewise the simple formula for
the standard error of the mean,
which was based on the square root law,
may not work anymore.
So then what's the standard
error in that case?
It turns out that in such situations,
simulations can be used to
estimate those quantities.
In fact, it may turn out that simulations
sometimes result in better estimates.
That what we would have gotten,
if we would be able to use the formula for
the normal approximation.