One thing to keep in mind is that since the sample is drawn at random,
the estimate will be somewhat off from the two-population parameter.
This is called chance error.
Also, keep in mind that if we draw another sample,
we will get a somewhat different chance error.
So we can think of the estimate as being made up out of three parts.
It should be somewhere close to the parameter.
There may be a bias if our sampling is not done well.
And finally, there's a chance error which is unavoidable.
So while the chance error is unavoidable,
it turns out, we can make it small by taking a bigger sample size.
Moreover, we can compute how large the chance error will be.
So, it's totally in our control to choose the sample size
large enough such that the chance error is sufficiently small.
And we will see later how to do that.
Things are quite different for the bias which is also called systematic error.
If we increase the sample size,
the bias will not get smaller.
Rather, it would just repeat the error on a larger scale.
Also, we typically don't know how large the bias is.
So, having a bias is a real problem,
and that's the reason why we use chance in sampling in order to avoid a bias.