Now, keep in mind that the outcomes of the 10 experiments are due to chance,
so the number of successes you see are random.
One set of 10 experiments might give you 4 successes.
Another set might result in 7.
For that reason, the number of successes is called a random variable.
To make the notation easy,
we simply write a letter for it,
like X just like in math,
but we use capital letters to make clear that this is a random variable.
So, on the previous slide,
we computed the probability of having 2 successes.
And in that notation,
that would simply be the probability that X is 2,
and we found that's 30.2%.
Since these were binomial probabilities,
one says that the random variable X has the binomial distribution.
Instead of computing the probabilities of all possible outcomes,
we can simply visualize those probabilities with what's called a probability histogram.
In the case of a binomial distribution with
n = 10 experiments and the probability of success of P = 0.2,
the probability histogram looks like this.
The probability histogram is simply a bar graph,
where the height of the bar shows the probability of the corresponding outcome.
For example we saw that the probability of getting X = 2 is roughly 30%,
and that's the height of this bar.
So here is the same probability histogram we had on the previous slide.
Now, remember we talked about histograms before.
In that case, we talked about histograms for data.
And histograms of data give percentages for observed data,
but keep in mind that the probability histogram has nothing to do with observed data.
It's purely a theoretical construct.
It shows probabilities, not data that have been actually observed.