Some people have suggested that when a student is grading other students' homework,
there might actually be a substantial learning effect.
Recently an experiment was done to figure that out.
Students were randomized into three groups,
with each group spending the same amount of time per week.
One group did homework only,
the second group did homework in peer assessment,
and the third group simply studied without doing any homework.
The final exam scores of that class were summarized by three boxplots.
You can see from the boxplots that the three medians differ somewhat.
But the question is whether that is sufficient evidence to
conclude that the three treatments result in different outcomes.
Of course in this case, the null hypothesis of nothing extraordinary is going on,
simply means that all groups have the same treatment mean.
Now if we had only two groups,
then we already know how to attack that problem.
We would simply use a two-sample t-test.
In that case, the t-statistic looks at the difference in the two sample means.
And, compares it to the standard error of the difference.
What we do in this module is we generalize
this idea to the situation where we have several groups.
This methodology is called ANOVA.