So now, let's look how we would go about actually doing a test.
The first step is to come up with a test statistic.
A test statistic measures how far away the data
are from what we would expect if the null hypothesis were true.
A common test statistic is the so-called Z-statistic.
The Z-statistic looks at
the observed outcome minus the expected outcome divided by the standard error.
Here the observed outcome is a statistic
that is appropriate for assessing the null hypothesis.
For example, when we toss 10 coins,
an appropriate statistic would be the number of tails, or maybe the percent of tails.
Expected here stands for the expected value of this statistic,
assuming that the null hypothesis is true.
Likewise, the standard error is the standard error of
the statistic under the assumption that the null hypothesis is true.
Let's look at an example.
Our statistic was the number of tails,
and so using the formulas for the expected values of sums,
we find that the expected value is 10 times the probability of getting a tail,
which is 5, and using the formula for the standard error,
we get the standard error for the sum is 1.58.
So, our x-statistic becomes the observed sum that is the number of tails, which is 7,
minus the expected, which is 5,
divided by the standard error, and that gives us a z-value of 1.27.