Let's look at another example to see
what normal approximation can do for us.
Recall that the 30th percentile is the
point where 30% of the data fall below.
So if I draw a standard normal curve,
then the 30th percentile
would be the z value,
where 30% of the data fall below.
Using a table of software,
one can find that that z is -0.52.
Now, we have to figure out how to
go from that z value to the 30th
percentile of the heights.
That means simply doing
the standardization backwards.
Remember that the z value is height minus
mean divided by standard deviation.
Now we know what z is, and
we already know what the mean and
the standard deviation is.
So we can simply solve for height,
all we have to do is plug in the numbers.
Now there is a second way
of doing this problem.
Remember z tells you how many standard
deviations you are above or below average.
So z = -0.52 means that the height is
0.52 standard deviations below average.
So the height would be the average,
0.52 standard deviations,
and then plugging in the numbers,
we get 67.4 inches.