So, I think a lot of the work we're doing is pretty unique in
this field in that, so we're certainly
not the only folks using data science in drug discovery.
But I would characterize a lot of these other efforts as going after either one type of
data generation, and sort of examining that data to see if there's some new insight there.
Or it's some sort of clever methodology to examine data that already exists.
And kind of that approach reminds me
a bit about the children's story of the blind men and the elephant, right?
When you're only inspecting sort of a small piece
of the entire universe that represents a drug or a disease,
you might look at that elephant as that blind man and
say it's a rope, or a spear, rather than seeing the entire picture.
And our view is, it would be much more interesting to
pull in the widest diversity of data you can get your hands on.
And then across that sort of spectrum of information,
help figure out, what's a false positive?
What's actually meaningful?
Help correlate a signal you see across
these very different datasets, and use that to help focus
in on what's the most likely drug treatment that's going to work for
that disease, and for those populations.
For us, we'd probably fall more in the category of translational bioinformatics,
which is saying we want to actually take data and
translate that into some medical intervention in some way.
And so yeah, there's different disciplines.
There's people who are just interested in raw knowledge and not
necessarily trying to produce a diagnostic, or a drug, sorts of things.
So there's lots of different ways that technologies in this field can be applied.