Now, let's have a look how big the confidence interval is.
Remember, the formula for the interval is we take
the estimate plus/minus z times standard error.
So the width of the confidence interval is given by twice z times standard error.
That term, z times standard error,
is called the margin of error.
So remember, the square-root law says that
the standard error is given by sigma over square-root
n. And what that means is that the width goes down as the sample size n increases.
However, because there's a square-root there,
that means that if we want to cut the width in half,
we need four times the sample size.
And likewise, if we wanted one-tenth of the width,
we would need 100 times the sample size.
Another option to make the confidence interval smaller is to make z smaller.
Remember, z is determined by the confidence level.
So we can make z smaller by choosing a smaller confidence level.
For example, instead of using a confidence level of 95%,
we could use 80%.
So there's a trade off here.
We would get a smaller confidence interval at the cost of
having less confidence that it covers the true parameter mu.
If we're interested in confidence intervals for percentages,
then there's a simple rule of thumb that allows us
to compute its confidence intervals on the fly.
The rule of thumb says,
just take the estimated percentage plus/minus 1 over square root sample size.
The reason why this works is because sigma can be shown to be
never larger than one-half no matter what the population parameter p is.
So, if we plug this into our formula for the standard error,
we see that z times standard error, where z equals 2 and sigma is not more than a half,
and those 2s cancel out,
and so, we are left over with that rule of thumb.
Sometimes, newspaper articles give
confidence intervals without stating a confidence level.
In that case, it's tacitly assumed that the confidence level is 95%.