The purpose of a statistical analysis is
typically to compare the observed data to some kind of reference.
Therefore, it's very useful to provide context in graphical displays.
There's a nice explanation of this in the book
'The Visual Display of Quantitative Information' by Edward Tufte.
One way to provide context in the graphic is by using the principle of small multiples.
We've already seen that the boxplot is very useful for this.
This graphic shows the temperatures that were
recorded at a weather station over 50 years.
It shows a boxplot for each month.
For example, this is the boxplot for January.
So it contains the data for the 50 recordings of January.
This display allows to compare how the temperatures vary throughout the year.
The reason why the principle of small multiples works well is because
the human brain is very good at decoding the information in these pictures.
Here's another example showing small multiples.
It shows the monthly unemployment rates for each state from January 1976 to April 2009.
Each plot is a time series plot.
That means on the horizontal axis,
we have time from 1976-2009,
and under vertical axis,
we have the unemployment rate.
The line that's given in each graph shows how the unemployment rate changes over time.
Moreover, there is an orange band which shows
a normal unemployment rate of between 4 and 6 percent.
By looking at these small multiples,
one sees immediately that there's a sharp increase in
the unemployment rate during
the financial crisis in states such as California and Michigan,
whereas things are not so bad in states such as Montana or South Dakota.