Modern software provides a lot of freedom to design one's own graphics.
There is a temptation to produce graphics that is flashy,
but often times that results actually in a poor outcome.
This is a graphic that shows annual donations to three universities.
Keep in mind that we are really comparing three numbers here.
There is a number for Harvard which is 683 million,
a number for Stanford which is
469 million, and a number for Columbia which is 359 million.
The graphic looks really interesting because it has three-dimensional bars,
but it is actually quite difficult to read.
One reason for that is because we are looking at three-dimensional blocks.
So we are thinking we have to visualize
volume when in fact we are just comparing heights,
but comparing heights is itself quite
difficult because you are seeing a perspective plot here.
The base of the three blocks is at different heights due to the perspective plot.
Now to help you see what's going on,
there are grid-lines in the background which
allow you to refer the height of the block to the corresponding number.
But as a consequence,
it is really quite difficult to compare these three numbers.
It would have been much better to put these three numbers in a dot plot,
which makes it much easier to compare them.
As another fun example,
look at the Gettysburg PowerPoint presentation by Peter Norvig,
Peter envisions what may have happened had
Abe Lincoln fallen into the trap of using flashy graphics.