So let's do an example to apply these rules.
Let's roll a die three times.
And we want to compute the probability that we get at least one six in the three rolls.
So, how would we do that?
So, one idea is to write the event at least one six as follows.
It could mean one six on the first roll, or
one six on the second roll, or one six on the third roll.
So, now we have or in between there.
So that suggests we should try the addition rule.
But there's a problem here, because those three events are not mutually exclusive,
because if we get a six on the first roll,
we can also get a six on a second roll.
So we cannot use the addition rule,
and we have to try a different approach.
So let's try the complement rule.
The probability of having at least one six in
three rolls is one minus the probability of its complement,
which is no six in three rolls.
So, why am I doing this?
No six in three rolls means no six in
the first roll, and no six in the second roll, and no six in the third roll.
So, now you see there's an and between the events,
and that's just what I need, because I know the three rolls are independent.
So I would like to use the multiplication rule.
And for the multiplication rule,
I have to use ands.
So, by using the complement rule first,
I put the whole thing in a position where I can use the multiplication rule.
So I can simply multiply those events and then I can just
plug in, because the probability of no six in the first roll is simply five six.
And by the way, that's another application of the complement rule.
So I get one minus five six, times five six, times five six.
And if you plug it in your calculator,
you'll see this is 41.4%.