In life sciences in general, data
science is being applied across
the spectrum, right? So we're working in
the earliest stages of drug discovery.
But there's certainly work that data
science can do to help optimize
clinical trials.
So part of having an effective drug
therapy is knowing in advance whether or
not that medication would work for
you, and
maybe you've had this experience, right?
You go to your doctor, you're not feeling
well, you're given a prescription, and
then the doctor says, and
if this doesn't work, right,
come back in a couple weeks and
we'll try something different.
And so part of what's going on there is
that your genetic makeup as an individual,
and sort of you as a biological entity,
you might react differently to
a medication than someone else.
And so, some of the other work
that data science can help with,
is some of those companion
diagnostics, right,
to figure out which treatments would
be most effective with which people.
This is not work that we do as a company,
but these are all opportunities where
artificial intelligence, data science
helps make people healthier as a whole.