The main topics in this module are
the law of large numbers and the central limit theorem.
The name central limit theorem comes from the central place
that this theorem has in statistics. So it's important.
But it's also important to understand that in every statistical analysis,
there are several histograms floating around.
The probability histogram which generates the data,
the histogram of the observed data, and the probability histogram of an estimator.
It's important to understand these, and to keep them apart,
and that's another goal of this module.
So, let's have another look at the distinction between a parameter and a statistic.
What's the average height of adult men in the United States?
That's quite difficult to get a handle on, because there are 120 million adult men.
But it turns out that one can estimate
this number quite well with a relatively small sample.
In this section, we'll see why that is.
Remember that the population in this case is all adult men in the US,
and there are about 120 million of them.
A parameter is something about the population we are interested in.
For example, the population average which we call
mu or the population standard deviation which we call sigma.
A statistic or an estimate is this quantity as it's measured in the sample.
That could be the sample average x bar, or the sample standard deviation s. So,
the idea is that we will use the statistic from
the sample to estimate the parameter of the population.