Regression is arguably the most important statistical technique.
It is extremely versatile, and can be used for problems where at first sight,
one might not have expected that regression is useful.
We will discuss the main ideas for inference and
regression and how to do regression diagnostics.
We will also look at some pitfalls.
The histogram on the top left shows the heights of 928 sons.
The average of the heights is 68.1 inches.
Now suppose we pick one of these sons at random and the task is to predict his height.
In fact, what one typically finds in statistics
is taking the average is in some sense the best predictor.
Now suppose we have more information.
Not only do we have a histogram of the heights for the sons,
but we also know the heights of their fathers.
The heights of these 928 father-son pairs are given in the scatter plot on the left.
Again we have to predict the height of a son,
but now suppose we know that the father is 72 inches tall.
Clearly this additional information should help us somehow in our prediction.
The reason for this is that if we know that the father is 72 inches tall,
then we know that they are somewhere among this group of fathers and sons.
And we know that for this group the heights of the sons are on the higher end.
What this means is that the additional information of knowing
the father's height should allow us to come up with a better predictor.
And that is precisely what a regression does for us.