Categorical data come up
when observations are grouped into categories
and organized into tables.
We will look at three important statistical
analyses for categorical data.
Tests for goodness of fit, homogeneity, and
independence.
This module is about categorical data. To see
what categorical data are, let's look
at this big tragedy from 1912,
when the Titanic sank and more than 1,500
of the 2,229 people on board died.
The question we can have is,
whether the chance of survival
depended on the ticket class. It
turns out very detailed
data are available about the Titanic disaster.
Here's a table that
shows the number of survivors and
people who died
for each ticket class, as well as for
the crew. This is a typical example
for categorical data. The data
are given as counts
for a fixed number of categories. Typically,
such data are obtained by grouping. In
this case, the data are tabulated
in what's called a 2 x 4 table.
That's because there are two rows
and four columns.
Such a table is also called a contingency table,
because it shows the survival counts
for each category of ticket class.
That means, contingent on the ticket class.
We will look at three problems
that involve categorical data.
They all use the chi-squared test.
These problems are testing goodness
of fit, testing homogeneity and
testing independence.