The square root law means that the standard error of
the sample mean goes down as the sample size increases.
This means that if the sample size is large enough,
then the sample mean will be close to its expected value mu.
This is the famous law of large numbers.
So keep in mind that the law of large numbers applies only for averages and percentages,
but it doesn't apply for sums, because we saw that
the standard error of the sum goes up as the sample size increases.
Also, we need to be sampling with replacement from a population,
or simulating the data with a computer from a probability histogram.
More sophisticated versions of the law of large numbers in
fact state that the whole empirical histogram of the data,
which is the second histogram among the three we considered previously,
would be close to the probability histogram if the sample size is large enough.