Let's summarize the main requirements for the central limit theorem to apply.
First, we need to sample with replacement or we need to
simulate independent random variables from the same distribution.
It turns out there are actually also
central limit theorems for sampling without replacement.
And in any case,
we know that if the sample size is much smaller than the population size,
then sampling without replacement is about the same as sampling with replacement.
And so, everything works out.
The second important requirement is that the statistic we are looking at must be a sum.
And remember that averages and percentages are essentially sums after multiplying.
Finally, the sample size has to be large enough.
The rule of thumb is that the more skewed the underlying population histogram is,
the larger the required sample size n. It turns out that if there's no strong skewness,
then a sample size of at least 15 will be sufficient.
For a stronger skewness,
we might need a sample size of at least 40.