Hello, my name is Guenther Walther and I would
like to come you to the introductory statistics course.
I'm a professor in the Department of Statistics at
Stanford University where I teach and do research.
I regularly teach a variety of classes from the introductory level for freshmen,
all the way to Ph.D. level classes.
I've been involved in developing the data science track in our Master of Science program,
which the Department of Statistics runs jointly with
the Institute for Computational and Mathematical Engineering.
Together with some of my colleagues in the statistics department,
I've also helped to create
a data science course that is accessible to all students at Stanford,
which incorporates many topics that you will find in this introductory statistics course.
Research-wise, I have worked in a range of
areas from investigating puzzling behavior in solar neutrinos,
to extracting information from many measurements of
single cells in high-throughput biological experiments,
to developing new statistical methodology.
One thing that I noticed when working in
these diverse areas is that statistical questions come up everywhere,
and that having a good grasp of the key ideas
of statistical thinking can make a big difference.