So, through my startups,
I had been working with with Paul Lee.
Paul was the former President of Electronic Arts.
He ran the show there for about 20 years before he started his own venture capital firm.
He invested in some of my prior startups and I was
working for him doing diligence at some other companies.
And so anyway, we were out to lunch,
and he sort of asked me, "Andrew, what the heck are you doing?
You've done all these startups and now you've gone back to school, help me understand."
And I told him about this project,
and I said, "I've been working on this really cool thing.
I'm using data science to find potential new drug treatments.
I got one of the best grades in the class on that project.
I'm really excited, I'm going to publish a paper on this, an academic paper."
And Paul has got this look,
when you do something really stupid, it's like, his face does this thing.
And he started to make that face and I was a little
baffled, right? I just told him how I'm living my dream,
I'm doing this thing that I'm so passionate about.
And he says to me,
"Andrew, you just told me this story about how you want to change the world.
Do you think you'll do that by writing a paper,
or you think you'll do that by filing a patent,
starting a company, and bringing this technology into the world?"
And so that conversation is just like a worm that dug into my brain,
and I kind of couldn't get away from it because he was right.
It was more than just doing something to be
impressive, and rather wanted to actually bring this technology to the world,
and do something meaningful with it.
And that was the beginning of the transition from
the academic world and to creating a new startup around that technology.