So here's a survey question
that's quite tricky.
What percentage of students have
cheated during an exam in college?
The problem here is that you cannot simply
ask students whether they have cheated.
Students may simply be too embarrassed to
answer truthfully, so what can be done?
This is being addressed with
what's called randomization.
It works as follows.
We do a survey that first instructs
students to toss a coin twice.
If the student gets
tails on the first toss,
then the student has to answer question 1.
Otherwise, the student
has to answer question 2.
Here are the two questions.
Question 1 says, have you ever
cheated on an exam in college?
Question 2 is,
did you get tails on the second toss?
So why are we doing this?
The answer we are going to
get will be partly random.
A yes answer could be due to
the student answering question 1 and
having cheated on an exam,
or it could be due to
the student answering question 2 in
getting tails on the second toss.
So a yes answer doesn't
really tell us anything, and
this should put the student
at ease to answer truthfully.
So if a yes answer doesn't tell us
anything, then why does that work at all?
So here's the key point.
We cannot really tell what an individual
yes means, but by looking at all
the answers collectively, we can actually
estimate the proportion of cheaters.
Here's how it works.
A yes answer can come from
either question 1 or question 2.
So we can divide up the event
of a yes into two parts.
This is the same reasoning that we've
used before with the spam filter.
So the probability of a yes answer could
be a probability of a yes answer and
question 1 was answered, plus
the probability of a yes answer and
question 2 was answered.
And now I simply plug in the formulas for
conditional probabilities,
and I get this.
What we are interested
in is this probability.
A yes answer on question 1,
which is the question about cheating.
So what we do is we solve for this
probability, and we get this expression.
So let's see, we know the probability
that question 2 was asked.
That's just a half, because it
depended on the first coin toss.
The probability that question
1 was asked is also half.
And the probability of a yes answer
given question 2 was asked, that's also
half because question 2 simply asks
whether you got tails on the second toss.
So the only thing which we don't know is
the probability that the answer will be
yes.
But this we can estimate from data.
In one survey, 27 students answered yes and
30 answered no.
So we can estimate the probability of
a yes answer as 27 over 57, which is 47%.
Now we plug in and we find that
the probability of a yes answer,
given question 1 was answered, is 44%.
So we can estimate that about
44% of all students have cheated
on an exam in college.